<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Pygments on Edd Mann</title><link>https://eddmann.com/archive/tag/pygments/</link><description>Recent content in Pygments on Edd Mann</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-GB</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://eddmann.com/archive/tag/pygments/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Using Python's Pygments Syntax Highlighter in PHP</title><link>https://eddmann.com/posts/using-pythons-pygments-syntax-highlighter-in-php/</link><pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://eddmann.com/posts/using-pythons-pygments-syntax-highlighter-in-php/</guid><description>&lt;p>Having a website that is heavily software-development based, one important aspect that can not be overlooked is well presented code examples.
Speaking on the importance of editor syntax highlighting in the &lt;a href="https://threedevsandamaybe.com/exploring-text-source-editors-and-ides/" rel="external noopener" target="_blank">previous episode&lt;/a> of our podcast, this attribute transcends to aid in the readability of code online.
Fortunately, there are many options to choose from.
You can either store the code snippets in an embedded &lt;a href="http://gist.github.com/" rel="external noopener" target="_blank">Gists&lt;/a> or use the front-end based &lt;a href="http://highlightjs.org/" rel="external noopener" target="_blank">highlight.js&lt;/a> or &lt;a href="http://code.google.com/p/google-code-prettify/" rel="external noopener" target="_blank">Google Code Prettify&lt;/a>.
One benefit that greatly simplified the publishing process when using a front-end based solution was that you could simply parse the Markdown file (perhaps with a class language type-hint) and leave all the hard work to the client&amp;rsquo;s browser.
As we all know, we have very little control over the viewing experience for each user.
And as I started to post more frequently, cracks began to appear in the syntax highlighters I had been using.
However, when looking for a solution, one had been staring me straight in the face all this time, and that was &lt;a href="http://pygments.org/" rel="external noopener" target="_blank">Pygments&lt;/a>.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>