<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Php-Extension on Edd Mann</title><link>https://eddmann.com/archive/tag/php-extension/</link><description>Recent content in Php-Extension on Edd Mann</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-GB</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 28 Aug 2015 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://eddmann.com/archive/tag/php-extension/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Developing a Resizable-Indexed Array as a PHP Extension with Joe Watkins</title><link>https://eddmann.com/posts/developing-a-resizable-indexed-array-as-a-php-extension-with-joe-watkins/</link><pubDate>Fri, 28 Aug 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://eddmann.com/posts/developing-a-resizable-indexed-array-as-a-php-extension-with-joe-watkins/</guid><description>Following on from our first screencast, which touched upon how to set up a PHP extension development environment and the creation of a simple &lt;code>array_sum&lt;/code>-like function. We now further this topic by implementing a resizable-indexed array class which supplies very similar functionality to that of the &lt;code>SplFixedArray&lt;/code> class.</description></item><item><title>PHP Extension Development for Beginners with Joe Watkins</title><link>https://eddmann.com/posts/php-extension-development-for-beginners-with-joe-watkins/</link><pubDate>Mon, 03 Aug 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://eddmann.com/posts/php-extension-development-for-beginners-with-joe-watkins/</guid><description>In the very first screencast episode of Three Devs and a Maybe, I was fortunate to chat with PHP core developer Joe Watkins, discussing PHP 5 and 7 extension development for beginners.</description></item><item><title>Introduction to Creating a Basic PHP Extension</title><link>https://eddmann.com/posts/introduction-to-creating-a-basic-php-extension/</link><pubDate>Wed, 12 Mar 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://eddmann.com/posts/introduction-to-creating-a-basic-php-extension/</guid><description>&lt;p>I recently decided to test my novice C skills in the field of building a PHP extension.
However, despite some very good resources (&lt;a href="http://www.phpinternalsbook.com/" rel="external noopener" target="_blank">here&lt;/a> and &lt;a href="http://devzone.zend.com/303/extension-writing-part-i-introduction-to-php-and-zend/" rel="external noopener" target="_blank">here&lt;/a>), there still seems to be a lack of beginner-friendly material on the subject.
In this post I will document a simple development environment that has worked well on a fresh CentOS 6.5 installation.
Once this has been set up, we will then move on to creating a simple &amp;lsquo;Hello World&amp;rsquo; extension, highlighting some of the extension platform&amp;rsquo;s capabilities.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>